William Russell MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
William Russell MD Papers
1904 - 1950
Nearly the entire collection relates to the institutional history Dr. William Russell wrote in 1945 entitled The New York Hospital: A History of the Psychiatric Service 1771-1936. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
1.67 linear feet (4 boxes)
Russell, William Logie, 1863-1951
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
FIC1989.0001
Unknown.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
William Logie Russell was born in New Brunswick, Canada in 1863. He received the degree of Doctor of Medicine from the Medical College of New York University in 1885 and held a variety of appointments prior to becoming Medical Director in 1911 of the New York Hospital-Westchester Division, then known as Bloomingdale Hospital. He was instrumental in planning and organizing the Payne Whitney Psychiatric Clinic of the New York Hospital, which opened in 1932. Dr. Russell was Professor of Psychiatry at Cornell University Medical College from 1928 to 1932. He continued in active service until his retirement in 1936. His interest in the hospital continued, and he compiled A History of the Psychiatric Service of New York Hospital, which was published in 1945. Dr. Russell died in California in 1951 at the age of 87.
Russell, William Logie, 1863-1951; Payne Whitney Psychiatric Clinic; Bloomingdale Hospital; NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital; Psychiatry--United States; New York Hospital-Westchester Division
Nearly the entire collection relates to the institutional history Russell wrote in 1945 entitled The New York Hospital: A History of the Psychiatric Service 1771-1936. This book was commissioned by the Governors of the Society of New York Hospital. The collection includes an annotated manuscript of his book and reviews of the manuscript. His research material, which comprises the bulk of the collection, consists of several photographs, typed transcripts of early hospital reports, Russell's notes, his additions and revisions to some parts of the manuscript, background information about early New York City history, statistics on the types of patients admitted and correspondence with the publisher, and reviews. There are typed abstracts of minutes of the Governors of New York Hospital and of the Asylum Committee, abstracts of laws and legislative sessions regarding the insane in New York State, and notes on general psychiatry before and after 1791 (1771 is the year a charter was granted to the New York Hospital; in 1791 it was opened for patients and the following year the first psychiatry patient was admitted). The association with Cornell University and the bequest from Mr. Payne Whitney for the psychiatric clinic and suggestions for its organization are discussed. Only a few of these items are originals, such as a report by Russell on the establishment of the Payne Whitney Clinic and a catalog of the Psychopathic Branch of the New York Hospital at Bloomingdale. Records not relating to Russell's book are a teaching schedule of Cornell University Medical College, a reorganization proposal for the New York State Department of Mental Hygiene, and merger information pertaining to the National Association for Mental Health. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Manuscript of book, chapters 1-7, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book, chapters 8-13, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book, chapters 14-20, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book, chapters 21-27, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book, chapters 28-34, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of book, chapters 35-36, appendices, reviews of manuscript, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Chapter 1, psychiatric thought in the 18th century, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 2, additions and revisions "Psychiatric Practice at the Close of the 18th Century, revised, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 3, source material, old New York, 1790-1831, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 3, additions and revisions, revised, old New York; medical, social, etc., 1775-1791, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 4, additions and revisions, revised, 1791-1808, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 5, additions and revisions, revised, 1792-1808, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 11, additions and revisions, material dealing with statistics and case notes, work copy, revised, 1824-1877, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 12, material dealing with treatment, revised, 1834-1850, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 15, abstracts of newspaper, accounts referring to poor conditions at Bloomingdale Asylum in regard to Frothingham, Van Vleck and Norton cases, notes on licensing, 1869-1888, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 19, work copy, revised, miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 22, extracts of Medical Superintendent's reports and letter on laboratory work, revised, 1895-1908, Undated (Box 2)
  - Chapter 28, charges of mismanagement, state supervision and laws, notes and abstracts, revised, work copy, 1851-1937 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with the publisher, reviews, related matters, and letter from Adolf Meyer, 1943 - 1946 (Box 2)
  - Visiting committee, 1808-1822, Undated (Box 2)
  - Inspecting committee, 1809-1851, Undated (Box 2)
  - Dr. Diethelm's abstracts of writings of Dr. John Galt and others, 1821-1840, Undated (Box 2)
  - Lunatic asylum, notes about Thomas Eddy, Samuel Tuke and an institution near York, Pennsylvania, 1808-1821, Undated (Box 2)
  - Benjamin Rush notes, 1810-1812, Undated (Box 2)
  - Minutes of the Governors of New York Hospital, 1771-1817, Undated (Box 2)
  - Stephen Smith, notes on history of care of the insane in New York, 1886, Undated (Box 2)
  - Minutes of the Asylum Committee, 1808-1821, Undated (Box 3)
  - State of the New York Hospital, excerpts from annual reports, 1808-1821, Undated (Box 3)
  - Medical Repository and American Medical and Philosophical Register, abstracts of case histories, 1801-1813, Undated (Box 3)
  - Letter from Dr. William Wilson to the Trustees of New York State Lunatic Asylum, 1841, Undated (Box 3)
  - General psychiatry, Drs. John M. Galt and Oskar Diethelm's abstracts, 1791-1898, Undated (Box 3)
  - State of New York Hospital, excerpts from annual reports, 1792-1808, Undated (Box 3)
  - General psychiatry, 1821-1894, Undated (Box 3)
  - Abstracts of other early mental institutions, 1821-1841, 1914 (Box 3)
  - Reverend John Stanford, minutes and memoirs, 1820-1835, Undated (Box 3)
  - Copy of John Stanford's first sermon in a lunatic asylum, for appendix chapter 5-6, 1819, Undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous quotations, 1847-1938 (Box 3)
  - Abstracts of laws and legislative sessions regarding insane in New York State, 1831-1921, Undated (Box 3)
  - Assorted committee minutes, 1852-1877, Undated (Box 3)
  - General psychiatry before 1791, Undated (Box 3)
  - General psychiatry after 1791, Undated (Box 3)
  - New York Hospital and the association with Cornell University, psychology and neurology vs. psychiatry, correspondence with George Canby Robinson, 1927 - 1929 (Box 3)
  - Bellevue Psychiatric Hospital, annual report, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Copy of will, correspondence and news clipping on bequest of Mr. Payne Whitney for psychiatric clinic, 1927 - 1935 (Box 3)
  - Bellevue Psychiatric Hospital, New York City Psychopathic Services, resignation of Dr. Menas Gregory, 1926 - 1935 (Box 3)
  - Excerpts on surveys of state hospitals in the U.S., used in connection with the History of Psychiatry in New York Hospital, 1937 - 1944 (Box 3)
  - Origin and Establishment of the Payne Whitney Psychiatric Cline of the New York Hospital" by William L. Russell, 1938 (Box 3)
  - The Society of New York Hospital, Department of Psychiatry "History, recent progress, the broadening field, extension of work plan", 1925 (Box 3)
  - Notes about Archibald Bruce and Thomas Franklin, Undated (Box 4)
  - Organization of Payne Whitney Clinic in regard to staff and salaries, 1931 - 1933 (Box 4)
  - Brief sketches by heads of departments at Bloomingdale's, 1895-1933 (Box 4)
  - Excerpts on administration, rules, etc., 1821-1840, Undated (Box 4)
  - Physicians' annual reports, 1841-1893, Undated (Box 4)
  - Recreational therapy, c. 1938 (Box 4)
  - Extracts from Bloomingdale Asylum minutes and annual reports, 1821-1848, Undated (Box 4)
  - Bloomingdale Asylum statistics, tables of admissions, annual and monthly reports of physicians and related material, 1821 -1840, Undated (Box 4)
  - Occupational therapy at Bloomingdale Hospital, c. 1920 - c. 1940 (Box 4)
  - Bloomingdale Asylum and Westchester Division, Undated (Box 4)
  - General history, notes from newspapers, publications, 1841-1852, Undated (Box 4)
  - Abstracts and notes of Bloomingdale Asylum physicians on discussions at APA meetings and on Journal of Insanity and other publications, 1851-1936, Undated (Box 4)
  - Biographies of Bloomingdale Asylum physicians, Undated (Box 4)
  - Biographies of Bloomingdale Asylum physicians, includes lists of staff and dates of association, Undated (Box 4)
  - New York Hospital and the association with Cornell University. Letters from Europe: G. S. Amsden, Adolf Meyer, George W. Henry, George E. Daniels, Gregory Zilboorg, Ernst Simmel, and others, 1927 - 1931 (Box 4)
  - Suggestions from other psychiatrists for organization of Payne Whitney Clinic, 1927 - 1932 (Box 4)
  - Suggestions from other psychiatrists for organiza­tion of Payne Whitney Clinic, 1927 - 1932 (Box 4)
  - Cornell Medical College Clinic, records of Westchester Division, notes, 1931 - 1943 (Box 4)
  - Catalog of The Psychopathic Branch of the New York Hospital at Bloomingdale, includes a history by Pliny Earle, 1904 (Box 4)
  - Psychiatry in Pediatrics, Payne Whitney records, 1933 - 1938 (Box 4)
  - Lists of periodicals pertaining to insanity, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Teaching schedule at Cornell University Medical College, 1932 - 1933 (Box 4)
  - New York State Department of Mental Hygiene Reorganization proposed by Russell, 1937 (Box 4)
  - National Association for Mental Health Merger information, 1950 (Box 4)